[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se Radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software okay welcome this episode of
software engineering radio brought to
you by I Triple E software is an
interview with Christos Ebert he's a
regular columnist with I Triple E
software magazine and his extensive
experience in software engineering in
practice areas Christoph would you
please introduce yourself hello my name
is Christoph Ebert I'm the managing
director of vector consulting services
we support clients around the world to
sustainably improve product strategy
product development and to manage
organizational changes vector Consulting
Services is part of the vector group
which has 1,100 employees worldwide and
serves practically all continents prior
to my current responsibilities I held a
number of global management positions
for 10 years at what is today I got a
Lucent I'm serving on a number of
advisory industry bodies and lecturer at
University of Stuttgart and some other
universities over the past years I've
authored several best-selling books
including the most recent book global
software and IT which is published by
our Tripoli and Wiley we will look in
this web podcast on lean development and
we will look into how it applies to
software and IT often lean is associated
with manufacturing we will show what the
principles are and how they apply in IT
and software projects and in doing this
we also refer to
a recent issue of I Tripoli software
where we looked into several case
studies on applying Lean principles to
software and IT ok great ok I think many
of our listeners are probably very
familiar with the topic of agile in the
area of software engineering but maybe
not quite so much with the topic of lean
software development could you perhaps
especially for people that are familiar
with agile how can you try to visualize
how agile and lean are related are they
very similar what are the different and
what are the commonalities and
variabilities between the topics with
agile and lean in the software space
lean has received currently a lot of
attention because it nicely balances the
need for value creation with the need
also to empower people to empower teams
and to move forward
with innovative products as such lean
development is a key principle to the
advantage of companies which sometimes
struggle in improving efficiency and at
the same time not strangulating there
aren t departments ok and is the would
you say that agile is very specific
typically for very particular projects
and lean is a more holistic more of
philosophy also a sort of it's like at
what might be clean yes I I think it's
relevant to see some distinguishing
points is why I taught a little bit
black and white looking h and more to
the development activities and lean
development more to the how to different
let's say projects different components
different features indirect but on the
other side I don't want to be that much
black and white with distinguishing the
two techniques as I just said they
enrich each other they relate to each
other
they certainly do not pose a kind of
it's either HL or
Slean and maybe in a moment we find some
time to kind of define lean development
and look to the key techniques which is
then easier to see but for now I see
those techniques enrich each other and
when I said earlier value creation is a
common denominator you can create value
if you want bottom up by looking how
you're doing things and how you can do
things better such as how can you be
more efficient in coding how can you
avoid defect in the first place and you
know I mean there's then something which
is called test-driven development which
is an HR technique where you think
before you write some code about how
would you test that code and in thinking
about the verification before the
instantiation you already avoid a lot of
defects now this very technique put to
the level of a product such as would we
need that feature for that market or is
it just an overhead is what we call lean
development and this is where I would be
very clear emphasizing that the two
techniques and rich each other rather
than it's one or the other okay okay
thanks I perhaps in another area that we
haven't gotten into yet is perhaps an
area of the people and the importance of
people I think that's perhaps a question
to you is that also another commonality
between agile and lean is the respect
for people the empowerment of the team
working together whereas in maybe some
other types of development it's people
are more view to sort of interchangeable
resources and so on and I think that
kind of feeling I don't understand with
that with either agile or lean could you
speak some to that because I know you
have a lot of experience also in the
right aspects laughing now XPrize at the
right time that I briefly sketch what
our key elements of lean and then you
will see that each of those which I
consider key
have their immediate sibling if you want
a brother or sister whatsoever in HL and
I said one of the five which I typically
distinguish that value creation and I
start with that one because it's giving
us the right scope and you're definitely
right a second one is people focus so
value is the perspective to the outside
which is what's the need of the customer
with eventually paying for the product
but the second one Emilia speak people
and teams and how can we empower teams
to be in a better collaboration how can
they be more responsive to immediate
questions how can they work together in
order to create the value then there's
the third one which is to eliminate
waste which is the dimension which I
mentioned earlier which you can see on
the coding level as reducing the defects
by applying intelligent techniques or at
the product level by avoiding that you
have features which later on would
increase complexity in the sense of Fred
Brooks the accidental complexity that is
things which are not necessary while you
do not really bring any value and that's
principle number three to eliminate
waste then a fourth one would be to
optimize the value stream that is to
look to different tasks how they relate
to each other and making those tasks
more efficient to for instance avoid
that the designer has to wait for a
colleague just because the work chunk is
not ready and if you put all these white
periods together or if you have a lot of
question answers because people do not
understand the specification that would
certainly be very inefficient so for
that angle to optimize the value stream
is a fourth principle and the fifth and
last of my enumerated list
this is to continuously improve and
again this is a technique which is very
key to any type of engineering because
if we would not learn in terms of
Technology in terms of process in terms
of our own skills and compounded
competencies we will not survive in
industry and we should never assume that
we are perfect neither our product nor
technology nor our processes nor we as a
person and if you put those five
together value people empowerment waste
reduction or elimination optimized value
streams and continuous improvement this
is what we call the key principles of
lean development already translated into
software development and as I said each
one of these five relates a little bit
to a child and for that angle they have
a lot of commonality and would be
distinguished just by the way you look
at it you look as you say you look at it
more holistically then it's what we call
in development if you look to it very
specifically from a perspective how can
I do my individual feature coding in a
better way that would be then more
related to a child principles okay all
right because that makes it makes a lot
of sense when we talk about the
difference - perhaps a beautiful to talk
about the difference also to lean in the
area of production and manufacturing in
what sense are is lean management in the
development area different I think
there's perhaps more variability in the
in the products we're not there's a lot
more uncertainty so I think perhaps one
has to apply lean in a slightly
different way I think Alistair Coburn
talks a lot about having the decisions
and information is what flows through
the
through the product and perhaps perhaps
that's a useful view so what what
differences do you see between lean as
it is the plot applied in manufacturing
and in these early phases like the
development areas yes I think it's
important to look to this difference
because often I see a kind of reaction
by software practitioners who would say
well lean I have heard a lot about like
Toyota Production system etc isn't that
only for car production and obviously
without any doubt this is where the word
comes from and historically there was a
link to production and only after a
while a link to engineering has been
built and what I want to emphasize is
that we should be clear that lean
production with its methods also having
been a kind of trigger is certainly not
what we now look in lean software
development there can be a lot of
parallels being seen I mean to eliminate
or avoid waste that is something which
you see both in production and in
software development rework empowerment
of people obviously they go all in
parallel
however we kind of confuse people if you
would take too much production oriented
example and this is sometimes a trap
which I see if people explain lean
development that they got stuck in these
commonalities rather than saying what
what is specific to software development
and you're definitely right that in
software there's a lot of differences
one of them as you mentioned with what
you consider information flow or
variability or the life cycle of
software which is all so much different
from product which is
manufactures and produced maybe by
robots that we should not look too much
to the commonalities except that there
is a historic point where liens of the
development branched off lean production
but this is so long ago and nobody would
today look too much back to those roots
but what we should certainly do and this
is the other viewpoint as practitioners
we should always be aware what's going
on in other engineering disciplines and
what can we learn by looking into other
industries this is my other criticism I
mean if one person would say well in
production is not for me I'm in software
that's fair because the product is
different on the other side as a
software engineer I would expect that
that person is open in order to also get
new stimulus like the stimulus we
received in architecture from civil
engineering and I saw software iecture
growing over the past 15 years initially
the stimulus for this push of software
tech sure that was coming from civil
engineering and from civil architecting
and this is something where I'm also a
bit careful specifically when I teach it
in school that people are not too much
and this is my discipline and I'm not
looking left and right I think
specifically here in attribute software
we have a quite strong background in
also trying to learn from the
application domains where software and
IT is actually deployed and this is why
I'm often interested how to other
engineering disciplines practice lean
and what can we learn from it in order
to evolve the in software development
and that's just I one example to be more
clear when we have been talking earlier
about the rework as a example which
applies both in HL as well as means of
the development it's something which is
unnecessary but now how do we
distinguish necessary from unnecessary
the a different technique
and one technique which helps us very
much has been coined by Al Davis many
years ago when looking to requirements
is that we have to apply a principle
called triage in order to distinguish em
based on a very few essential questions
what's the contribution of that specific
feature to the overall product now if we
look where does this triage come from
well comes from medical it's a key
principle if doctor arrives as an
emergency case and were a couple of
people are lying around that is as one
doctor not much chance to have ten
persons in parallel he applies triage to
find out where with his help at most
value at the very moment and this kind
of principle and insights would not
really ripple into our industry and
fertilize our industry if we don't have
this background from other disciplines
yes that's a good point so we can use
that to prioritize and so on yeah so I
think that's very true that we can take
the best out of the agile space take the
best out of the the lean manufacturing
areas and grow your own that fits your
own organization and its needs as
appropriate yes okay that makes a lot of
sense maybe we should go through your
various points I mean let's start with
the value creation which I think has a
lot also to do with the requirements
engineering area that you're also very
very active in what is a good balance
there
to some time one says there's one should
do a lot of upfront design make sure you
do it right the first time you hear
sometimes out of the lean space but on
the other hand you sometimes also hear
the term decide at the last possible
moment so what's your what's your take
on that when do you how much do you do
upfront and how much do you try to delay
yeah I mean both is true and I think
clearly we should understand both
principles not as
kind of contradiction but as enriching
each other um what we should definitely
avoid is that we exaggerate on the
analysis part which is what we call
parallel spy analysis because that slows
down very much and we should be aware
that we can never specify to the last
detail so what is the key difference
here is to understand in the beginning
what are those requirements which create
most value for whoever is the user or
customer and that can be an entire
market share or in a new product it can
be a new distinguishing feature while on
the other side also keep flexibility be
it now for the individual product
because some of the requirements are
just uncertain as is almost the rule in
specifically software and IT projects or
be it to preserve a sound variability
for the evolution of our product the
course what we maybe we want to go into
different markets maybe we want to have
low and the high cost or price version
of our product in other words when we
start with a product or when we start to
elicit requirements the key question in
the beginning is are these requirements
valuable now obviously if you ask the
person the question that blunt any
customer would always say yes of course
and he would probably be the wrong
customer to say no and I just gave you a
garbage can of things which we never use
and so it has to be telogen ly evaluated
for instance looking from different
viewpoints looking from different
profiles these are all requirements
techniques which are today very much use
but essentially just to do what I called
earlier the triage that is identify
those which have highest value where
somebody would pay most for and I give
you a simple example which I sometimes
of life people would just always come
back and say well our requirements are
all high priority we need all of that
and we need it now and you know these
kind of things
that you have a list of let's say 100
requirements and you sit in front of a
couple of people product people
whatsoever and them then you just give
them $100 in their hands and you would
ask them so now you buy your features
and I know there are a couple of other
people in the room would also buy
features so they have to split their
investment intelligently also it's a
game it turns out to be very effective
because they surgically put money on
certain content and it gives you in
almost all cases a 50/50 split which is
rather clear of what are those
requirements which have a value on which
are those which are if you want nice to
have and this is one of the key
principles of value now another one
which relates very much to the topic
which we called eliminate waste is to
also understand which of the
requirements which of the features has a
big impact on architecture and those
obviously also have to be understood in
the beginning because if there's a big
architecture impact we better do it
right in the beginning a good example
are the so called quality attributes
like security usability etc which should
be evaluated very well in the beginning
because doing those things light means
to lose a lot of time and to have a lot
of rework yes that's an excellent point
I really appreciate whenever you talk
about this this area you always
emphasize that it's not just always what
the customer says that they need but you
really need to fully understand what the
customer really wants and really you
know dig deep enough to know that the
customer really wants these things like
performance and scalability and so on
and not just what they say but what they
truly need to address that hmm yes
that's a good point yeah I need a lot of
soft skills that's my experience with
this whole topic of deciding in the
beginning what are we going to do and
how relevant it is because it's not the
plant negotiation where you say well you
know you give me that
requirement and if you do it fast I
don't need that other requirement I mean
this is not what I want to tell us but
rather - together with the customer
evolve develop the requirements and in
fact it's a quite interesting evolution
in the requirements engineering and in
value creation that some ten years ago
we were speaking about requirements
collection or gathering requirements
until the community realized there is
nothing together I mean as as soon as
you start to collect requirements you're
already on the wrong track and what is
much more important is to develop
requirement to elicit to find out
together with customers together with
people who really understand the market
who really understand the needs in the
future what would be the right
requirements and if you only collect
things because others have done it
already in their products you're always
behind so this was a key learning over
the past decade and again this is
something which equally applies to a
child development as well as to lean
development just looking from different
perspectives okay perhaps in another
aspect associated with your first topic
of value creation perhaps one can also
interpret value also as the knowledge
that you that you get in some of these
cases I know for example there's the
topic of set-based decision-making which
comes I think from the lean
manufacturing area where you try you
keep your options open and you have you
allow various alternatives to be alive a
longer period of time it sort of is
frustrating sometimes for the managers
or typical macho manager wants to say
you know you know just bang is fist on
the table and say just do it just decide
which way you're going to go and do it
and bring the project to the end but
perhaps one of the things that one can
do in lean is also to try to keep your
options open and because even if you
throw one of those away it's not waste
because it brings you value right it's
not the artifact itself but that
knowledge itself is
valuable I think let's definitely true
and actually you mentioned two very
valid points the one is that we
continuously learn and even in
evaluating different designs or making
an explicit architectural decision or
explicit decision which part of the
system to test more thoroughly than
other parts we continuously if you as
you say throw away something and keep
others and I recall in one of the very
big learnings also in the past 10-15
years was that we faced a lot of
decisions under uncertainty that holds
by the way for all engineering
disciplines but we'll talk about Sofia
NIT so we need techniques to prepare
such decisions and we have later on also
to efficiently execute the decisions as
another story but a key element which is
often overlooked is that in order to
decide we need alternatives and
comparing evaluating these alternatives
based on criteria is something which is
even today not so often done often we
just shoot out of the hip we have the
gut feeling maybe we put three four
different alternatives aside each other
but finally we jump very fast into one
without having really clear evaluation
criteria and this is bad because we
often have conflicting targets take a
textual decision where you want to have
a very efficient system at the same time
with a high security level and you want
to decide to which decreed will you
evaluate individual packages on a
network or can you cluster that doing on
a bigger scale which would be more
performant but may be lighter lighter
easier to break these are all
alternatives and in evaluating the
alternatives we learn and that learning
clearly is a value creation even if we
would not deliver the one or the other
feature in the end
the other aspect which I consider
equally relevant is that at the moment
when we have options to decide that we
also evaluate when should they be
decided what's the timing and I said
earlier sometimes it's good to do that
early because it has a lot of side
effect if done wrong with a lot of
rework sometimes it's good to do it late
or and this is more and more relevant or
even keep it open forever in a way as we
for instance do today variant design
that we keep some variation points where
we can switch in a efficient way between
different implementations just to make
sure that said earlier you have a low
and a high price version of your product
that you can point and sell and upgrade
by a remote switch and not buy a lot of
variants coding and and all this kind of
anticipating decisions and planning the
decision at the right moment is the
second important learning when we think
in terms of eliminating waste okay great
maybe that's a good point to go over to
the to your second principle that the
people focus because those are the
things that you were just now talking
about have to do with the learning and
the experience if you can't have that
logical way to decide between the
alternatives and you really have to rely
also some more on the experience of the
people it makes sense to not view people
sort of resources that you can just plug
in and plug out at will so I think in
the in the lean area I believe one tries
to empower the team as much as possible
and put a lot of value that they are
well trained and that that you have more
distributed intelligence and distributed
decision-making in the teams I think
that's a very important part of lean do
you have experience in that area or can
you comment on that
yes empowerment to me is one of the key
success factors and again it's a
principle which we practice in lean
which we practice in HL which you find
in many other management theories for
instance if you see the evolution of
Peter Drucker's work from the
organization level to the individual
level you see this learning effect much
earlier than anyone in software has
practiced it but you say very much in
the beginning that still we often see
the very hierarchical decision-making
what lean means with the empowerment of
teams is that in order that the team can
take decisions and take the right
decisions you also have to give
knowledge to the team you have to give
the team these skills so that they have
an understanding of the background and
this is something which we often
hesitate to really implement because
what it means is seen from a distance is
the neck is first of all that is team
kind of doing things which are not
really the business I mean they for
instance if you understand the business
of their of the customer they have to
understand relationship to other modules
components etc they have to understand
feature in the action they have to
understand roadmaps where each normal
manager would say why the heck should
that team understand all these things
they should I think logically they also
don't want to let go somehow yeah
exactly
that's one of the reason the other one
is clearly that it's just considered
additional effort which some about
somebody has to pay on the other side
once you practice it really in let's say
grown organization you will realize that
these teams are smart enough not to
waste their energy on things which are
entirely pointless but they would ask
questions where they know there could be
impact and I've often worked with teams
on this evolution path from being more a
directed
which would get more less an order of
the day as I call it as we see it in
military for instance words only also
make some sense in some situations but
which is not at all really productive in
software development where you have so
many uncertainties and unforeseen
constraints that it's good that the team
has the certain as unnecessary
background in order to decide and this
transition sometimes is a speaker
challenge for the line managers as well
as for the team and you're definitely
right at the moment when the team gets
this kind of I call it in quotation
managerial skills obviously they grow
while their line managers fear that I
will have looked anymore so much to do
but let's be clear I mean who are the
companies which are the companies which
really have the steepest growth and
competence and ultimately in in value
creation with a single product these are
typically startup companies and the
reason for that is that each one in this
team has a very profound understanding
of content environment and business and
this is why they are so fast in in
creating new things and what we need to
establish is that this principles can
grow independent of the company be a
small of it a very big multinational
company and it works I've seen
transitions into lean development with
team empowerment in very big companies
such as companies with many thousand
people working worldwide in an
engineering and still at the moment when
you empower the teams and you let them
in a certain scope move in that
direction you would see that the overall
motivation was fast growing and I think
it happens probably fairly quickly does
it does it happen fairly quickly in your
experience that once the the line
manager sees that
the team can make those decisions and
make them correctly and effectively
episode it depends on three factors the
other is the three factors one is
certainly where do they come from
and if you know if they have very strong
line management principles it's
certainly taken more time because all
the genes of engineers and managers are
of the other dimension now a second
principle is the context of the work I
mean if you have small projects which
are rather individual or independent of
each other it's much easier to
understand to install a team
responsibility than if you consider a
project with 200 plus peoples working on
a single objective as we often see in
avionics or automotive or medical or big
IT projects a third dimension finally is
to which decree are the people and their
environment really prepared to do it
because if the team would be hesitant
because suddenly their responsibilities
increasing I mean you have to face it
empowerment is not just something which
you receive as a present it's also a
thing which needs a clear focus that you
have to deliver and if the team or the
the group of people is not really so
much interested into taking this
responsibility it might never succeed I
have seen such situations where even the
chins were not there the projects were
rather isolated but the people had
somehow the attitude we are paid as
engineers so we should not take a
business decision and this can really be
the blocking factor in the end mm-hmm I
think it must be clear from the top
management that that one really is
willing to take take these risks and to
encourage such a activity than make it
clear
there's really a culture change I guess
yes okay I don't need help to give the
teams a small let's say responsibility
to change and iteratively let it grow
that's my success recipe here rather
than time well as of tomorrow you are
fully empowered to curse and it's really
just a slogan but if you if you
gradually grow considering these three
sectors which I mentioned earlier
typically it works out okay look I think
that that was a very useful about that
team responsibility and one of the
topics that isn't most associated with
the topic of lean is the waste which was
eliminating waste was one of the third
topics that you had mentioned could you
speak some to that especially in the
area of the different levels if you have
individual projects or you could have
whole organizations because I think I
like to say that maybe one one person's
waste is another man's treasure you know
how do you do you really do people
really have the same understanding of
what is waste in in this in this context
yeah I think to understand waste that
really means to look at the task at hand
and look also to the product this is why
I started my list with value because
once you have understood what's value
it's easier to think if you want
negatively in terms of what's waste and
you already mentioned earlier that we
should also not be bluntly saying
anything which is not immediately
generating a feature which you can sell
next day it's waste I mean that that
would be a to shortcut perspective
learning can be very helpful and we
discussed it earlier so I think it's
important similar to what we just
summarized about the team growing
also the waste consideration is
something which you learn gradually some
type of waste is rather easy to
understand I mentioned earlier clearly
it's waste if a defect would be detected
too late
clearly it's waste if you implement the
requirement which later on nobody wants
but okay who gives you the criteria and
who would give you the let's say
verification techniques to find all the
effects right away if it was that easy
we probably wouldn't even need so much
different methodology but there will
challenge is to to learn on the way
based on product and business
understanding what is waste in what I'm
currently doing and maybe also
occasionally get the step backwards to
find out as you chest that is what I'm
doing currently may be generating a
value for the next increment or for the
next release while for the immediate
release it might be even a waste of time
or might be in an unnecessary circle a
key example which we often discuss in
industries to which degree should I
document what I'm doing there been times
where in a child development techniques
would be emphasized which would say what
the code is the documentation which
could be right if you have throwaway
software but sometimes this is not the
case and industrialized professional
software which has maybe also to follow
certain standards or which could be subs
substance to some liability of the
product needs to be well documented now
what does it mean to document code or to
document architecture to document the
test strategy this is certainly not
something you learn in school and this
is what I mean
- stepwise build these skills and then
also get an understanding because many
people are
maintenance and then they are new
development so they know over time how
much documentation what type of
documentation is helpful in order to
correct the defect in a previous release
and how much documentation would be the
boundary where you would have rather
overhead in your current product
development and this is what we call the
good enough principle which is the word
where I'm quite careful because I often
in critical industries such as avionics
automotive or medical where you're quite
careful not to do things which later on
would be considered wrong or where you
would have done not enough in order to
have the right say safety and integrity
levels but it's clear that we should get
experience in how much is necessary how
much is good enough for what is expected
from my work as a professional engineer
and that depends on industry that
depends on the user's expectation and
this is something which needs business
sense and which needs also a profound
engineering understanding and this is
what the team's will learn over time
when they move into lean development
okay perhaps in the area of waste we
were talking before about requirements
engineering so things like
overproduction and developing the wrong
product very well you know having
features that the customer never really
wanted I guess those are some obvious
ways of obvious things that are that are
waste but I think it really makes sense
to use this term to consider lots of the
things in the software engineering space
for example again with an example from
the lean manufacturing if you had some
some tooling device that needs that has
a cost of associated with changing the
tools that this hardware device has this
is I think it's called a motion type
waste and it's similar in software
development there's this waste associate
with the context switching and while
there's many people that are in you know
this one key expert is involved in five
different projects and the management
often neglect to consider this context
switching of this person's brain is
costing you know twenty percent of the
person's time or somesuch I think it
it's useful to use that I think to call
attention to the management of this not
good situation yeah that's very true
that often we run into such situations
and should be quite careful that if we
develop and if we follow a certain say
development path that of a product that
we understand about features that we
understand about wise and that we also
understand from the perspective
requirements what's necessary what's not
necessary and play historically and we
have a lot of examples and I will
mention one just as a key point to
summarize from our previous discussion
we come to that tooling change if we
take netscape browser which has had
initially a huge market share of 90 plus
percent and declined in a few years
against the Microsoft Explorer that was
something which you would never expect
an Internet age that somebody could lose
if he was once one or two years ahead
but the real deficiency in a Netscape
product was an uncontrolled complexity
growth without any architecture without
any project steering without almost any
documentation not even a real project
management and these different factors
together can read a product extremely
fast even if it's a market leader with
90 plus percent market share and these
are the kind of stories which we should
always keep in mind and we should learn
from history
in order to avoid that we repeat it now
what you say about changing tools and
context which I think we know very much
from our background and operating
systems that in any context which always
means that we have to store something
that we have to take up a new variables
which obviously needs time and we have
done a couple of studies and there's
also studies reported and specifically
in psychology that too much fondant
context switch too much tasks which are
pseudo paralyzed actually severely
reduce productivity of a person and of a
team and the typical value which you
should reach is two or three things
which you do say pretty much in parallel
which helps to reduce a white cycle
which could receive a result from a
single task which you do on the other
side if you have five six or seven
coding projects in parallel and can
easily one from the other project calls
you because you need some interface
equipment or I need some explanation
then your context switches will not only
kill your efficiency but will create a
lot of defects we have seen for instance
in projects close to handover were a lot
of these activities happen in parallel
that the defect rate under time pressure
with different parallel tasks triples or
gets much higher than the initial defect
rate just because with that stress
almost no UN being can really cope not
just to be clear when we talk about
parallel tasks I mean the engineering
task if you have an expert who would be
let's say doing architecture and systems
engineering activities maybe this senior
person would be able to cope with four
or five such different products in
parallel but the broad experience
from individual perspective is that we
should limit to two to three and not try
to do too much in parallel and this is
again also a learning for organizations
which are often faced because they would
say well I have that specialist I need
that specialist as you said in five
projects what should I do
I don't have the skills to replicate and
what I tell them is replicate and it's
very very tough not so much because of
the individual engineer I mean they feel
rather good and certainly empowered if
they can learn more about a broader
field but their management they think I
have this expert why should I pay if you
want the cost to ramp up to three others
while again it's a good HR principle to
work as a pair because if one is sick if
one is absent the other one is still
knowledgeable about what is Pierre had
been doing and this is how I try to
introduce the principles that it's
common sense that we share our knowledge
it's common sense that we help each
other and it's common sense that we do
not have that single specialist who we
cannot really replace and once this is
understood it's also easier to really
thrive on empowerment okay well that's
fascinating upgrade I'd like to move on
to the the fourth topic that you had
mentioned at the beginning optimizing
the value stream or also the flow this
is a topic that I think is extremely
important we had Donald Reinertsen
as an expert in the area of the flow
topics and product management in the
lean product management and he gave a
talk at Siemens about a year so ago to
many of our colleagues in the area of
lean and in development engineering and
he has a very strong focus on queuing
theory and focusing on not and
optimizing the capacity use utilization
of the people these resources in the
but instead to focus on the the workflow
and to focus on the throughput of the
whole system and it has some maybe
connotations of context to the traffic
jams that we have sometimes on the
German Autobahn right if there's too
many people you're trying to optimize
these individual capacity utilization
and you can really get this huge traffic
jam and nobody goes it goes anywhere so
I think optimizing the flow is perhaps
even an easier thing to control than
budgets and schedule I think I think it
probably makes sense to have more of the
knowledge on this queueing theory topics
which I think you're probably also well
known in the lean manufacturing area but
software people don't seem to know them
very very much yes in them in a nutshell
what is behind is that often
specifically we have fragmented teams
and organizations and tasks somebody
would do something pass it on and you
have not only the previously discussed
context which is but you also have a lot
of white you have a lot of tasks which
is a correctly queue up somewhere you
would have bottlenecks situations like
the before-mentioned specialist or
because some resources such as a given
infrastructure and testing is not
available I recently work with a client
who need a rather big amount of very
specific test environment and one of the
key bottlenecks was to get into this
test lab and then really efficiently do
tests now if you have too much if you
want incremental builds for their
context it would not really work because
they have extremely expensive test
environment so they try to apply queuing
more from the perspective of how can
they most efficiently use their test
infrastructure so queuing and the value
stream analysis as we call it is very
important the history is indeed traffic
analysis mostly in Telecom
occasions um and it applies as you say
also for traffic and all other things
but a good exercise is actually just to
sit down and draw a picture together
with different functions in the project
or in a product development and see what
are the interfaces how often are things
passed back and forth and the initial
picture always looks very very crowded
with a lot of small activities and what
then has to be understood is how can you
cluster certain activities like the
empower teams how can in the face be
reduced
how can bottlenecks be reduced with
different mechanisms such as like
replicating some competence or
infrastructure or maybe outsourcing some
activity whatever I mean there are
different ways to approach it
but the biggest iOpener which i know in
this whole picture of value stream
analysis always the first time when you
have this picture ready often we just do
it with post-it notes on a whiteboard
and show it to the team once it is
finished because often they only know
their own that's the environment and
they would turn this out while we sorted
the whole time but we never really
looked at it that way and even if you
later on would not really be able to
let's say f1 team with five persons who
would do anything end-to-end because
that could also be inefficient reducing
certain in the faces looking to where
did we have in the recent project a lot
of back and forth of activities like
insufficient requirements which had to
be reworked five or ten times or bit
further on if you have a project
organization which is very much
functional but not so much in terms of
end to end perspective of what's the
product which we deliver all these could
then generate very useful discussions
the team's how could this stream of
activities be simplified and this is a
very helpful exercise do you think that
may be part of the benefit of that
approach is even just getting those
people all together in one room and in
front of a big wall full of post-its and
and discussing that in person too just
to meet and to understand these people
that you don't maybe don't at meal that
may be the requirements engineering
people don't ever meet the testers in
person and to discuss right
currently it helps to look to the right
and if you want slices of that whole
picture what's only makes no sense is if
you have a rather big team we'll try to
draw the picture themselves first they
typically don't have the technologies or
methods how to draw such a picture and
second they would focus very much on
what they know and only guess now what
we often do is that we see together with
say smaller teams and sometimes
individuals and stepwise generate that
picture then it's SSID I open not to
bring in these teams I just look at it
and discuss it and relate it to their
own experiences and then if you want to
draw some circles with red color around
certain hotspots and then give a team
for internal give to teams like the
requirements engineer and the tester a
certain hot spot and I look here we have
too much iteration which are rather long
and very costly because in tests you
find out that the specification was
wrong or something was missing why don't
you do a review of the requirement for
testability which by the way is to my
experience over many years is one of the
most effective and productive review and
inspection techniques along the whole
software development cycle and suddenly
they would better understand how do I
have to document my requirements spec
while the tester would probably much
earlier understand and what's the real
purpose of
system and in doing this kind of hot
spot improvements used fi to move
forward okay so but do you have some
examples of of cases that that have been
able to fairly easily take on these
approaches that we've been talking about
or if you have recommendations on what
first steps are for people that are
interested in pursuing this further um
you're not talk about all these five
principles or you talk about the value
stream analysis overall of all while a
meantime we have a variety of examples
and I think as a word of caution we
should not expect that lean is something
which has ten principles or sound so
many clearly defined techniques which
you do in fact I even have seen just to
stick to our previous example one
company where they completely check to
rated on queuing to a level which was so
theoretical I mean they applied real
queuing equations that it was pointless
because you cannot could not anymore
really find out what to do different
this is why I said it's easier to have
the picture and then dr. hot spots and
then use common sense in order to
improve those yeah there are a couple of
very good examples where over time
companies had introduced it and I think
since we mentioned earlier this I Triple
E special issue it could be quite
interesting just to look to these issues
that timber October 2012 where a couple
of case studies have been presented and
one which I like very much is one coming
from medical device development and at
Siemens where a group of people have
looked into a set of different lean and
a child principles such as
operations such as incremental
development etc and they have shown that
an intelligent mix or blend or whatever
you call it of certain principles
together with the right education and
competence management only from a
requirements perspective yielded 30%
efficiency improvement in that specific
platform development environment or
another one which we have been looking
was an empirical study which had been
done on the effect of Kanban and
scrum in different companies small and
medium-sized companies and again
independent of the industry there were
different industries there was a clear
experience that is really what we just
discussed in terms of waste and value
stream that these principles got a lot
of value in the companies which were
doing it in other words there is today
already a set of good examples from
which we can learn case studies such as
mentioned from a table software special
issue but also a lot of others and I
recall when we received the papers of
that special issue I think we receive 23
papers so you see there is today already
a lot of knowledge around on the other
side I know also from my own background
there is an equal amount of companies
that try and fails because they
underestimate the emphasis on change
management I mean we talked a lot about
change during these different
introduction cycles and if you over do
if you overload a team you can end up
like in a little cartoon where the post
also say well as of tomorrow you're
you're empowered so what I mean it's not
enough and
this is why I change management is also
something to be seen as very critical
success factor one of the big benefits
perhaps of lean is that it makes those
cycles probably so short so that you
really have a chance right you have
these very quick feedback cycles you can
learn very very quickly we've had these
traditional waterfall projects that went
for two years and by the time you learn
something the business has totally
changed then we had agile and iterative
processes where this feedback loops were
much smaller and I think with with Lean
perhaps it's a good closing note I think
perhaps that these ability to learn
quickly and to adapt survival of the
fittest feel like Darwin is perhaps
that's one of the reasons also perhaps
that it's more popular that there's more
possibilities to learn and learn also
from failure and the successes that you
have right a key principle of economies
improvement is that you really apply it
continuously and again if we look for
instance to scrum if you have these
daily stand-up meetings where one key
element is just that you are able to
share some experience and you can do
that in a small and can do that in a
bigger context and I think it's very
important that you step back let's say
every evening or every Friday or so and
say okay what can I learn what can we
learn as a team from what we have
achieved and where we may be well not as
good as we had hoped or expected okay
well it's been a very fascinating a
conversation with you Chris also I
really appreciate your insights into
into this topic I think it was a very
interesting and I think I hope that our
listeners will also find pieces that
that they can apply in in their practice
practice practical work yes and I think
it's always good to stay with them when
they have
looked into some of the materials which
refer to simply use also contact sent in
email or whatsoever I mean the contactor
was mentioned actively software and they
would certainly get into a rich arena of
expertise to draw benefits from right
and perhaps write articles about them in
the future absolutely so we can
consciously learn from each other there
you go okay well thank you very much
okay thank you goodbye thanks for
listening to SC radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to support us you can advertise su
radio by clicking the Digg reddit
delicious or slash buttons on the site
or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]